AN AGE OF ILLUSORY MAGIC…
A person.
a fleet.
A war.
a man.
an idea.
a little trick.
a ruse to bring down the walls of Troy.
And burn it to the ground amid screams!
What does that mean?
A gift.
About Athens.
We have gods in common.
Please accept this gift.
Save him from the waves!
Take it to the temple of Athena.
The war is over.
One person
a fleet
a war
a man…
Stop!
Not that song.
Mommy's little boy!
Run. run. little guy!
Run!
I want to remind them whose fault it is.
I don't want the song about Odysseus.
I want Odysseus.
So why are you entertaining suitors at his house. then?
In this world. men
do whatever they want.
And as for me—I'll do what I can.
I'm a man now. Mom.
Then kick them out.
Break the Law of Zeus. and you'll see
what they'll do to you if you give them a reason.
I've already lost one husband.
I don't want to lose a son. too.
Dad is coming back.
So where is it?
Eight years since the fall of Troy.
It's been almost twenty years since he left us.
Where is it?
He deserves the same
welcome as all of you.
Are you calling us beggars?
I'm saying that you've been
welcome here for three years now.
We've been enjoying your
hospitality for so long.
just because your mom doesn't choose.
She's already married.
Odysseus is dead.
What do you know about my father?
That you had wretched livestock and bad wine.
You got the best
during the first two years.
And I know he never came back.
Not yet.
You miss your dad. even though
you never even knew him.
Like a whiny little brat.
Since no one knows
who his father really is.
Don't think you know who mine is.
I. however. knew him.
When we were kids. We used to watch him hunt.
I wanted to set out for Troy.
but he told me to stay.
so I can keep an eye on you.
Me or my mom?
How could anyone not look at her?
My father is coming back.
And he won't be as generous as she is.
So he doesn't follow the Law of Zeus?
The law instructs us to treat
strangers the way we would like to be treated ourselves.
because they might be gods in disguise.
And I think it's become clear.
Antinous. that you are not a god.
Well. this one here didn't exactly smell like a god.
That wouldn't be a good disguise.
Be careful.
It might strike you right now.
That thunderclap was pure luck.
I don't know. You have wise eyes.
The Eyes of Athens. Here.
Are you in cahoots with the merchants?
From Sparta.
Did Menelaus return from the war?
Years ago. Didn't Odysseus return?
We don't know if he's alive. Do you know anything?
The story of how he won the war.
We've already heard that. Anything else?
No.
But Sparta is full of
veterans of the Trojan War.
Someone's bound to know something.
Are you Odysseus's son? Go to Sparta.
Go. Go to Menelaus.
He'll welcome you warmly.
The queen wants to speak with the foreigner.
He lives for the news.
No. no? Don't give me false hope.
Somehow. he can tell if someone
has actually seen Odysseus.
Do you see that one?
He's almost blind. but that doesn't stop him
to beat to death the travelers
who lie about my father.
No. no. That's too fast.
And how do you know that?
You don't need eyes to
sense a sudden maneuver.
Mentor. push him.
No. no. That's way too fast.
He's just as friendly as you are.
You just obeyed your father.
Where did you find him?
They met right here.
Come.
I'll take it.
Is that for your son?
Like a hunting dog.
And he was right.
Don't move. Do you really want a scar that badly?
Why do you always make the bow ring?
That's fair.
Should you warn the prey?
To fight with honor.
But this isn't a battle. You're hunting.
Hunting is a cautious battle.
Very clever. Yes. But that cleverness
is going to get you into trouble.
Try again.
Now. not so fast and not so precise.
You don't win with perfect defense.
Lure the attacker.
What?
- Hesitation.
Expose your abdomen to
the enemy's weapon.
His attack is your chance.
Did you teach my dad how to do that?
No. no. He taught me.
You used to say. “You won’t always be
the strongest or the fastest.
"So be the smartest."
And what would he do?
What if you locked all the suitors in your house?
No. I don't even dare to
imagine what he would do to them.
There are so many of them.
Take out two. and the rest will back down.
Rude people and cowards.
Many people could have gone to Troy.
but when Agamemnon arrived.
Their fathers hid them.
And he knew that Agamemnon's war
would take many years and claim many lives.
And he mustered his army by drawing lots.
Name?
- Sinon.
Pull. No.
Name?
- Antinous.
Weigh.
Yes.
By drawing lots?
Antinoüs told me that he had proposed to her.
I think they're up to something.
Your son wants to go in place of Sinon.
I won't let him go.
He needs to stay and
take care of his family.
She can take care of your son. too.
Of course.
Stay with me.
Did he want Antinous to take care of me?
No. no. no.
But Odysseus was sensitive
to his father's grief.
He felt sorry for the fathers.
You and your mother meant
more than the promise of glory.
You knew it would take years.
Did you tell my mom?
Ask her.
Eumeus. will he ever come back?
Argos believes so.
I've never seen a 20-year-old dog.
And he has already outlived his owner.
I didn't mean to interrupt you.
I'm in no hurry to go anywhere.
According to the elders. when
I finish your grandfather's shroud.
I'll have to get married.
Why?
Ithaca had been without a king for a very long time.
They want protection.
Against what?
The Maritime Nations.
These are just stories told by travelers.
That's how we learn everything.
That's how we learned about the fall of Troy.
And now everyone is talking about
the attacks by the seafaring peoples.
And who are the maritime peoples?
No one knows. but the elders
want us to be prepared.
Shall we get ready?
We are part of the largest
known civilization.
Look at that huge house.
Stones as old as knowledge itself.
Left at the mercy of greedy
guests who are not welcome.
Its construction is nothing
if its meaning is not taken into account.
The Law of Zeus.
Treat others the way
you want to be treated.
They take advantage of the situation and ruin everything.
And how can you even think
about marrying one of them?
Because a long time ago
Your father asked me to do this.
Agamemnon is our king.
And the Trojans abducted his daughter-in-law.
Or she left with them on her own.
Anyway. They say that
the walls of Troy are impregnable.
And we'll sit outside and wait for them.
provoking them to fight.
And so the years go by. And Telemachus grows up.
And you're learning to live without me.
Menelaus may give up on Elena.
For Agamemnon. this is an excuse.
Troy must stop
controlling the trade routes.
He won't let this chance slip away. Never.
What if you refuse?
He's going to take our son.
He wouldn't do that.
He sacrifices his own
daughter for a favorable wind.
Why do the gods want his daughter?
The power of self-sacrifice lies
in how much it costs.
It's monstrous.
And he shows determination.
I won't be back anytime soon.
If I ever come back at all.
What if we run away?
On your fastest ship.
With your best crew.
And we set off toward the horizon.
Holding hands on
the deck. rowing toward the sunset.
chasing the setting sun.
There's more to it than meets the eye.
Agamemnon's vengeance
will come down upon all of Ithaca.
Promise me that.
If I don't return
and when Telemachus came of age.
Promise me.
that you'll get married again.
Enough with the sacrifices.
Love is not a sacrifice.
Of course it is.
And I don't want you to do that.
It's not up to you.
Promise me that.
Promise me you'll come back.
What if I can't?
Then the memory of you
won't make decisions for me.
Take my brooch.
Always carry it with you.
Athens will bring you back home.
I don't think it would suit me.
When passengers say they've seen them…
I'll ask them what you were wearing.
That way I'll know if they're lying.
If the sea peoples exist.
At the moment. Ithaca has no
king who could raise an army.
I… I could take the throne.
Come.
Place the bowstring on the bow.
That's not fair.
He said that only he could do it.
He liked it when others tried.
You were putting all the axes in order.
Yes.
No one has ever succeeded.
Mom. they're ripping us off.
to choose
one of them. before he ascended the throne.
My companion told me that Menelaus
had returned years ago.
Everyone came back.
Those who survived.
He may have died.
If that's the case. this is my palace.
We need to understand.
I need to go see Menelaus and find out.
Telemachus.
The suitors want to harm you.
Do you think I don't know?
Every evening. they wait for me to give them a reason.
And outside the home. out at sea. on the roads?
They won't be short of
reasons. You won't be coming back.
You don't want me to lay claim to the throne.
You want to keep me in my place
so you can remain the queen of Ithaca.
I'm tired of being queen
of Ithaca without my king!
Without your king?
Or without "some" king?
Do you think you can
take your father's place?
You're just a kid.
What a commotion. Melantius.
Don't step in with your spurs.
You're a cowherd. not a horse herder.
And you're a pig. Who do
you think you are. talking to me like that?
The servant whom your master
has put in charge of his shepherds.
Our master
left a long time ago. you blind fool.
And you're just as welcome as that dog.
Argos!
Argos.
Master. he hasn't done anything.
Is that you who stinks?
Leave the dog alone.
Which one?
- Both of us.
What did you say. slave?
- He got carried away.
It was my father's hunting dog.
His hunting dog?
Well. look at that.
Bring it out. We want to eat.
No! Can't you see that he's in pain?
All right. I'll put him out of his misery.
Leave him alone!
Did you see that?
Have you seen it yet?
He attacked me!
I have the right!
Please!
Please don't hurt my son.
Okay. Okay. Polib.
He's lost his mind. Have mercy.
Look. Have some more of his wine.
I'll take care of it.
That was his hunting dog.
She lives only to see Odysseus return.
Okay.
He goes to the outhouse.
so that he could be the first to greet his master.
The dog stays outside.
Think carefully before
taking a risk for an animal.
Euriclea.
Deliver provisions to the ships.
No one should know.
Surround yourself with trustworthy people.
You're going to break your mother's heart.
If I stay. they'll make me fight.
No one will support me.
I need to find out about my father.
So it will help me if
they realize that Odysseus is dead.
The grooms won't let that happen.
You won't come back alive.
Tell Mentor to wait for me
on the ships at dawn.
What do you want me to tell your mom?
To last as long as possible.
The ship is ready. The tide is favorable.
Have I ever told you that you have wise eyes?
The Eyes of Athens?
A few times.
He didn't ask where we were going.
Where are we going?
Let's find my dad.
He's alive. I can tell by the wind and the waves.
It's out there somewhere.
wandering. wounded. lost—I don't know.
But he's alive.
More dreams?
Generous people.
Closed.
In the darkness.
The reflection of a fire on a rock. I don't know.
Don't you want to remember?
Why don't the gods speak
in a way that we can understand them?
Who doesn't understand the thunder?
Or the fire?
A child's smile. a bountiful harvest?
But they're hiding from us.
Look.
Who runs the cloud?
Is he calling the birds?
Who controls the water?
Who were you talking to?
Athena came to see me again.
He tells me to remember.
I'd better go.
Why would you leave?
We have everything we need.
How long have I been here. Calypso?
I have a home.
There's someone there.
How do you know?
I don't know.
I'm sorry.
What we have may last forever.
Eternity is for the gods.
Are you a goddess?
You want to remember. but what
if that puts an end to your happiness?
So it wasn't real.
No.
Not anymore.
- But I like it.
Stop eating from the lotus.
Tell me what you remember.
After Troy.
Troy.
We won the war.
And then what?
Ten years on this lousy beach.
Let's go home.
Remember those we left behind.
Will the provisions be enough?
We've brought quite a bit from Troy.
One more stop won't kill us.
And… pull!
Put the oars away.
Break!
Put away the oars!
Hoist the sail so we can
follow the southerly wind.
That's so true.
Agamemnon sailed westward along a safe route.
He brings more people along with him.
We'll find a place to stay.
Is that so? That's risky.
I had followed Agamemnon long enough.
With a little luck and a favorable wind
We'll see the world. after all
We'll get there before Agamemnon.
Quiet!
Keep to the right.
Odysseus!
Earth!
Do you see?
That damn lucky guy.
We're running out of supplies.
Prepare an advance party.
Food and water. For three weeks.
What if they don't give it to us?
How much do you want to go back?
Get your weapons ready!
Sifting.
asking for a loan.
grabbing.
Ask why they ran away and didn't come out to greet us.
They think of us as a seafaring people.
No.
We are Greeks. From Ithaca.
Did you know we won at Troy?
We're heading west with the south wind.
He says that if we continue down this path.
We won't like what we find.
After years of war
Nothing could come
between my people and their home.
Even me.
And then something happened.
Chasing a fugitive.
That damn lucky guy.
No. no. no.
Sheep don't walk on their own.
Let's follow her.
Someone lives here.
Yes. He makes cheese.
It's pretty good.
There are many.
We have to leave.
We have nothing to trade.
The Law of Zeus.
I don't know if the person who lives here knows that.
Or Zeus.
Everyone knows about the Law of Zeus.
Light the fire!
We'll greet the host.
Stay away from the fire.
Spread out!
I think he's asleep.
Wait.
The Rock.
We can't move it.
We're trapped.
Pass it on.
In the morning. when he takes the herd out.
We ran toward the exit.
Take a break.
Come on. come on!
Run!
Can we wedge something into the rock?
To leave a gap?
Maybe.
But what?
That guy.
He'll notice.
Grab it by the end. Put it in the fire.
How many ropes are there?
How many sheep?
Two dozen.
There are a lot of us.
When he comes back. the two of us have to leave.
Or be killed.
Run in a crouched position through
the herd. and then scatter.
Just to catch one.
Yes.
The four of us have to run.
Two by two.
Why take any more risks?
He ate two last night.
He'll eat two more before he goes to sleep.
Run. run!
And what about his body?
What about him?
Are we just going to leave it there to rot?
So that thing can eat it?
We honor our dead. Odysseus.
He died helping us escape.
We honor him by running.
Father Poseidon. they've blinded me.
Revenge. Dad. Revenge for my pain.
Poseidon. avenge my pain.
He can speak.
Why didn't he speak up sooner?
Do you talk to ants?
Should we work things out with him?
I think it's already too late.
What are you doing?
No!
Come on. Run. run!
Let's go!
Hop on!
Come on. come on!
- Come on!
Let's go!
Why is he shooting?
That beast killed good soldiers.
Yes. and that beast was also the son of Poseidon.
What?
I heard him call out when
we gouged out his eye.
That thing was a monster.
I heard the same thing. too.
Is the sea against us now. too?
And the wind.
How will we get home
with Poseidon against us?
We cannot live solely
on omens and sacrifices.
Do you know how many times I heard you praying?
to Athens. since we left Troy?
Couldn't you have shown some mercy?
Take it.
Put it on.
So that you may remember those we did not bury.
The gods help
those who help themselves.
Ever since then. every stormy sea and headwind
You told them that we were cursed.
But where is my crew?
When will you let me see them?
If I were talking to them.
Maybe I would have remembered.
Did I have a husband?
Children? Maybe a son.
How long have I been here?
Quite a while.
If I had a son.
How old would he be?
I don't know how to talk to a king.
You'll do just fine.
Just don't say a word.
But if anyone asks. we're merchants from Crete.
We'll approach the king.
Welcome.
Thank you. That's all…
From here.
Where are they taking us?
The king is determined to meet with the foreigners.
Sit down.
Not you.
You.
Enjoy the hospitality.
As Zeus commands.
And then. maybe. you'll tell us who you are.
It's a nice day to come.
It's a celebration. My daughter is getting married.
Tomorrow he's leaving to start a new life.
You don't look like a beggar.
I guess you know who I am.
I am Menelaus. son of Atreus.
Agamemnon's brother.
Elena's husband.
You've heard of Elena.
The person for whom
a thousand ships set sail.
Today. maybe just five hundred.
So many died on
the plains of Troy because of him.
Because of your brother's ambition.
This one looks like someone.
Ajax…
Patroclus…
Achilles…
I don't miss them as much
as I miss one particular warrior.
The smartest of us all.
We've been rotting away on that shore for ten years.
In a stalemate.
Arguing while one
He couldn't figure it out.
Odysseus.
Have you heard the story about the horse?
Is that someone from over there?
We were there for days.
Crammed in before the ship set sail.
He knew. No one
was supposed to know we were inside.
Nor Sinon. the soldier we left behind.
During the first high tides.
some of us drowned.
We were there. silent. surrounded by urine and feces.
A gift.
About Athens.
We have gods in common.
Do you appreciate the gift?
We have to burn it.
Burn him! Burn him!
This is a gift for Athens!
A Gift for Athens!
The ports!
I knew we had to
wait for a moonless night in Troy.
Come on. come on!
They're attacking the city!
- To the gates!
To the gates!
Run. run!
The city is under attack!
Let's go!
Come on. come on!
And you already know the rest.
Does my story move you?
You should hear the bards.
I've already heard them.
But they weren't with you.
With your father.
Odysseus.
You look so much like him.
Where did you say goodbye?
In Troy.
The gods granted us a just victory.
Fair…
They gave us a well-deserved victory.
without blessing our journeys.
It took me years to return home.
But he didn't come back.
Others returned and regretted it.
Tell him.
Tell him about your brother.
- No.
For what the gods
had decreed for him after the just battle.
No.
- For welcoming him as a hero.
- How Agamemnon Returned Home
years ahead of us.
- No.
How did his queen receive him.
my twin sister. Clytemnestra.
No. No.
- Tell him that she…
No! He doesn't want to know about my brother.
And as for his father.
I don't know anything about Odysseus since he left Troy.
Nothing?
Not even any of your people?
Nor those of Agamemnon.
the merchants. the travelers?
Do you want rumors? Is that what you want? Gossip?
You're in the right place.
Does anyone want to tell
a story about Odysseus?
Some say he's rich.
Others say he's poor.
Some say he is dead.
Others say he is in prison.
What do you think?
- Locked up?
Which prison?
Would you arrest a man like that?
Tell me what you remember.
The rest will fall into place.
The men were convinced
that he had offended Poseidon.
All set!
Pull!
And… pull!
We faced one storm after another.
Off Course
until we really got lost.
And… pull!
Pull!
Row!
Hi.
We come in peace.
All we need is food.
We need food.
Do you understand me?
- It's just a child.
If this is a child. what must the parents be like?
Hey. It's nothing.
No. no. no.
Run! Run!
To the ship!
Come on. come on. Come on.
Back! Back! Come on.
Run! Hurry up!
Give me the bow! My bow!
Let's go!
Come on! Come on!
Row!
Wait!
And… pull!
Let's go!
Wait!
- Pull!
The oars!
All right! Get moving!
To the left.
Follow the shore.
What if they have ships?
We need to get as far away as we can.
We don't have the resources to sail blindly.
We lost our way.
We need to find some food
and regroup.
Port side.
There!
Smoke!
Head over there; there'll be a place to
drop anchor on the beach
The oars!
Form an assault team.
Tomorrow!
Have someone keep watch.
We want you to stay.
Who?
- All of us.
Those of us who are still alive.
Is this a rebellion?
It's up to you.
Give me your bow.
I'll make sure we have dinner.
It doesn't matter what you find.
No. no! Everything's fine!
Don't hurt me!
- Calm down.
You're right!
- No!
We won't hurt you!
If I do what you say.
No one is going to hurt you.
I'm Evriloch. What's your name?
Circe.
Circe. we need food. Right away.
I have some food.
A lot of food.
Let me.
Weapons. armor
Put them in the back.
Do you like my meat?
Why… do you have so many?
You never know when
strangers might show up.
Men.
With their appetites.
"Hard" is never enough.
Eurylochus!
They didn't come back.
No one?
- No.
Give me your knife.
Stay right there!
Why don't you come closer?
Are you coming from the sea?
Are you alone?
My pigs liked you.
Are you hungry?
Leave your weapons by the door.
Enjoy Zeus's hospitality.
Get a pig. You can
slaughter it for dinner.
Whoever you are. you're obviously not a farmer.
Give it to me.
The stew smells good.
That's enough for both of us.
Who says there are two of us?
Who else is here?
Who. right?
You say you're alone.
But no one comes here alone.
Right?
You can only get there by sea.
Where are your companions?
I'm looking for them.
Has anyone been here?
But did you prepare all of this?
Are you questioning me? You?
A traveler dying of hunger.
who hasn't touched the food.
He claims to be a sailor. but
he wears the armor of a great warrior.
And it violates the Law of Zeus
by carrying a dagger into his landlady's home.
You have a keen eye.
Sharpened by the gods.
Do you have visions?
Truths.
Sometimes.
Would they tell you where my people are?
Your people?
That's right.
They would do it.
Would you tell me?
If you give me your knife.
Why should I help a liar who
rejects my hospitality?
Your people were here. but now they're gone.
Did they move forward. for example?
And did they leave their rings behind?
I wouldn't do that.
No!
I don't know who the raven is.
But if you don't let him go. I'll
strangle him. and he'll find out.
Don't hurt her.
Is he/she related to you?
Your mom?
Your sister.
He turned her into one. just as
he turned my people into pigs.
I haven't turned them into anything.
Look at them. That's just how they are. Look at them!
Despicable. Disgusting.
With base instincts. valued in battle.
They raped and looted
everywhere because of you.
Do you think they're acting
against their nature?
Do they do that just because you tell them to?
A true commander believes
that brutality is discipline.
But you don't seem naive.
But you sent them to me.
At my place. by herself.
Some filthy soldiers. with
empty stomachs and hot blood.
Did you think they would respect me in my own home?
Look at them!
Look at them.
Did they hurt you?
They were going to do it.
They just want to go home.
Leave them alone.
Come back.
Go back to your costumes.
Go back to your disguises.
Come back.
Come back. Come back.
Go back to your disguises.
Come back.
Odysseus.
Go back to the ship.
Take as much food as you can.
Leave the meat.
You can't let her live.
She's a witch.
Who gave us strength?
Your gods.
Fill the bladders from the stream.
We set sail at dawn.
Why did you leave her like that?
That way. we understand each other better.
I'm sorry if we offended you.
We can't go back
without your help.
To reach
the trade routes.
You've really lost your way.
What?
Only the blind Tiresias
can show you the way.
Tiresias?
In Hades.
No one swims through
the Underworld.
And he returns.
You'll come back.
Go north.
Toward the sunset.
And he went further inland.
Where the river of fire
meets the river of ice…
Dig a trench.
Fill it with
sacrificial blood.
Gather the dead.
And figure out how to
get back home.
You.
Not your people.
Did you curse them?
It's not a curse.
It's true.
They don't want you to
provoke the gods.
The gods say that
only you will return.
Then I challenge them.
Synonym.
I am Odysseus.
Let him drink. Odysseus.
Then you'll hear
his confession.
Odysseus?
He fooled everyone.
And why me?
I needed you to
believe me.
Why was it proposed?
Don't you remember
how I got here?
I asked you to take
Antinous's place.
It fell on him.
Offer money to
your family for your spot.
If the Trojans
don't let me live…
If I never
come home.
Take this to my father.
Tell him everything
I did.
Odysseus.
Feel free to
add something of your own.
Couldn't you have
told me the truth?
You knew I would die for you.
The dying man confesses.
You should have believed him.
I died for you on that beach.
I know. I was there with you.
I heard you repeating
that lie with your last breath.
And it brought us victory.
I was there. Right there.
Smelling your blood.
What comfort
does this bring me?
Without knowing you were inside.
until the dead told me.
Which dead people?
Many veterans of your
campaigns wander along these beaches.
The dead come to mourn the living
and to welcome the newly dead.
My father found me first.
To comfort you.
Shadows bring no comfort.
They want news about the living
who have offended them.
My father had died in poverty.
alone. sifting through
people like Antinous.
Did Antinous deceive you?
And she's definitely tricking you. too.
- How?
Who is taking care of
your wife and son in Ithaca?
My wife isn't a problem.
Talk to Agamemnon
about his return.
Is Agamemnon here?
You buried me with
honors in Troy.
Thank you.
But think about those
who weren't there.
It's not always possible.
When you get home.
take a ship.
Set sail for the unknown
West until you discover land.
And there. offer a sacrifice
and honor your people.
Do you still have that tree?
Of course.
If you manage to get home.
Restore Antinous's shame.
I'll do that.
My lord.
Odysseus.
Why are you here?
We won the war.
You were on your way home.
Odysseus. the most brilliant
of all my generals.
I hope you don't end up like me.
Have you. too. been left
to fend for yourselves like us?
My misfortune was
to return home.
To be greeted by
my beautiful wife.
I want to take a bath.
Anointed.
Reassured.
To learn the hardest lesson.
"Had I poisoned her heart?"
Which already belonged to someone else.
No! No.
She and her lover?
They had been planning my death for years.
Odysseus.
My son. Orestes.
did you avenge me?
My lord. how am I supposed to know?
I'm still trying to get home.
Don't make the same mistake I did.
Don't cross the threshold.
expecting wreaths and praise.
Go there after you've changed.
Don't rush.
Analyze.
Do you see?
I know what I need to do.
Partly.
My prophecy is not meant for their ears.
Go to the ship.
Go southwest.
Beyond the sirens.
They lure men to the cliffs.
Everyone dies.
I won't let that happen.
I'm going to plug their ears. With wax.
After the sirens
You choose between Charybdis.
the whirlpool.
and the monster Scylla.
The whirlpool in the sea
takes everyone's life.
The Monster—Only Six of Them.
But your determination not to sacrifice
any more lives is killing them all.
I'll do what needs to be done.
Finally. when
famine and rebellion threaten.
They lead you to the shore. where
the Sun God's cattle graze.
They sacrifice
Apollo's cattle.
Zeus kills them because of this.
Do you see?
I'll stop them.
Why do you value their lives more than
those of the ones you've already lost?
I can save them from the gods.
But not from them themselves.
What is this?
Those he did not bury.
Who demand that you
share in their shame.
Let's go!
Let go of the ropes!
We have to set sail!
Is this our fate?
We rowed from the underworld.
leaving so many comrades behind.
I have to save the others.
What happened to them?
Did they leave me here?
Will they come back?
Did you do something to them?
Take some.
She told me not to eat the lotus.
Just tonight.
So you can get some sleep.
And tomorrow. when you're ready.
you'll remember.
You'll remember your crew.
And for his family.
Family.
Wife?
Do I have a spouse?
What are you doing?
Everything's fine. Melanto.
No strangers allowed.
With or without the curtain.
After three years of feasting.
we're no strangers. Penelope.
Do you want to marry me
or ruin your reputation?
Melanto won't speak.
Actually. I came because
I'm worried about your reputation.
Everyone can see how hard you work.
Slow but steady progress.
But every night you undo what you've done.
Leave us alone.
Don't expect him to be loyal to
a master he has never met.
I expect him to be loyal to me.
He will be loyal.
When you marry me.
Slaves can be
loyal only to the future…
And this house is waiting for an owner.
And the kingdom of Ithaca is waiting for a king.
The King of Ithaca will return.
No. There isn't.
Did you know that when I was young
Did I try to go with him to Troy?
He never told me.
He refused to let me go.
He knew that Ithaca. without him.
would need a future.
And he saw me as part of that future.
I will never tell
the grooms about your deception.
Finish the weaving.
You have to let him go now.
Why would you marry
someone who loves someone else?
Your loyalty to Odysseus is one
of your greatest virtues.
I love you.
I want you to choose me and
put an end to all of this.
Don't tell me you're not tired.
From waiting.
Because of the uncertainty.
He has already fulfilled his duty…
Year after year after year.
You need to think about yourself.
It's time to live.
Odysseus would have wanted that.
I'll give you whatever you need.
My queen.
And what about my son?
The throne is his.
He is the heir.
Unless we have a son.
Where is Telemachus?
He went inland.
To see his grandfather.
He's lying.
He set sail on the sea.
He went to find out about his father.
Where?
In Sparta.
At Menelaus's.
Are we going?
No.
You're always so loud.
Melantiy. for a cowherd!
You were eavesdropping.
- No. no.
No. No.
I came for Argos.
The dog is staying there. Go
back to the farm.
We'll send Melantius
to pick up your pigs.
You're no longer welcome here.
old man.
I obey only
my mistress.
Does she even know your name?
Go away.
Telemachus will return
through the temple in Pylos.
Wait for him there with your people.
And you're left to
woo the queen?
No way.
He must die along the way.
Iro has a plan.
I want him and his men dead.
In a ditch. With their throats slit.
Telemachus and his men will
be on the lookout for bandits
on the way from here to Pylos.
But if we first take the temple away from the priests…
And bring me something
from him as proof.
His nose.
Is that how you'll recognize him?
And his ears. too.
Who taught you that?
My father's pig farmer.
The Pig Farmer.
Yes. his most loyal servant.
Odysseus left behind his most loyal servant.
He's always been the smartest.
The only one
Agamemnon would listen to.
She should have listened to him more.
So what happened to your brother?
His wife betrayed him.
He killed him.
What did you do to them?
His son. Orestes. killed them both.
What? His own mother?
Avenge your father.
You don't need to worry.
Your mother isn't like Clytemnestra.
That might be the case.
The grooms convinced the elders
that she should get married.
This is no time for an empty throne.
You know how it is. The maritime nations.
Were they attacked?
No. but the attacks
seem to be getting closer.
Sparta is ready.
But what about Ithaca?
He must gather an army
to defend himself.
Someone has to take the throne.
The battle is over there. not here. son.
He ran away from the problem.
He left his mother with the grooms.
Should I hire mercenaries?
To kill them all?
To kill wealthy and powerful
guests in your own home?
They'll kick you out.
So what?
You must drive them away without
breaking the Law of Zeus.
I must take the throne.
I need to know if
Odysseus is alive.
This has nothing to do with a father
you've never known.
You need to take control.
Regardless of Odysseus.
You have to remember.
No. that's not true.
I don't need to
know the truth.
I'm happy here. With you.
Then why are you gathering
the wreckage of your ship to make a raft?
Remember your crew.
His trip.
The Song of the Sirens.
Put wax in their ears.
Not me. Tie me to the mast.
Why?
I want to hear the song of the sirens.
No.
That's a bad idea.
No one survived.
That's exactly why.
I'll be the first.
Even if I beg.
don't untie me
until we get through it.
Check their ears.
Extra rations for
anyone who says. “Yes. sir!”
What is the song of the sirens?
It is everything
you want it to be.
And then—everything you
wish you hadn't wished for.
That sweet itch.
the one you just want to scratch.
but you can feel it deep down.
You can't catch up to him.
Although it's sweet.
it becomes unbearable.
It tells you that what
you want most.
That's exactly
what you won't have.
And what you
can no longer have.
It's what you already had…
And you lost.
It was the song of the promises
I didn't keep.
And you said that I didn't want
to go back home.
Foam in the water!
Foam ahead!
Charybdis.
The Monstrous Whirlpool.
Hoist the sails!
Come on. hurry up!
Weigh anchor!
Are we going out to the open sea?
He's already caught us.
Let's go!
To the north! Get moving!
Toward the canyon.
It's very cramped.
He headed toward the whirlpool.
If you're walking along the edge.
It might take us to the other side.
Don't worry. We'll manage.
No. No!
We're heading to the canal.
Take it easy.
- To the canal!
Paddles inside!
Put away the oars!
Right oars.
get ready to stop!
On my signal!
Three.
two.
One!
Hi!
Pull out the oars!
Hold on!
We did it!
We did it.
The gods are with us…
Row!
Stay the course!
Pull!
You already knew that.
And he didn't tell us.
We weren't going to go through here.
And those men would still be alive!
No!
We were all going to die.
You had no right!
I had every right.
And all the responsibility!
The whirlpool was going to
destroy us all.
That's how we live.
Just a few!
Yes!
What else did Tiresias tell you?
I'll dock there.
You can't go there. That is
the island of the Sun God.
We need to repair the ship.
They're exhausted!
We lost six!
We're about to dock.
We'll take a break there.
Everyone is going to die!
Did you ask what
Tiresias told me?
That everyone will die.
If they sacrifice
the livestock to the Sun God.
who lives on this island.
Everyone dies.
Okay.
We're about to dock.
We'll cook our own meal.
We're getting some fruit. Water.
Nothing more.
Swear to it.
Everyone.
Do you see?
The wind brought us here.
We took a break.
We repaired the ship.
And we'll set sail
as soon as the wind changes.
Grab that rope.
Did you keep your promise?
Yes.
Quite a long time.
But the wind didn't change.
The steady breeze that
allowed us to dock made
It's impossible for us to set sail.
We're out of food.
Go away.
Did you think that if you ate in
silence. God wouldn't hear you?
We thought you wouldn't hear us.
I'm not the problem.
I wanted them alive.
Tiresias told you that.
Circe. The gods told you so.
Gods do not speak in order to be understood.
Isn't the pain obvious?
Blood or death?
When you watch them die.
do you see a coincidence?
or consequences?
I see the consequences.
I see my failure.
What if their death is
their failure. not yours?
I'm leading them.
I brought them here.
And who about you?
Are you greater than God?
Why are you taking responsibility?
Why don't you want to come back?
What were you expecting?
They ran out of food.
Have mercy on me.
My mercy brought us
to this cursed island.
I told them what was going to happen.
That's right.
And we chose to drown
rather than starve to death.
All right. Now's the time.
The wind has stopped! There's no wind anymore!
The lull lasted long enough
to lure us into Poseidon's sea.
Under the sky of Zeus.
The bow against the wind!
Port side! Port side!
Pray to the gods!
The bow against the wind!
Ask for forgiveness!
The wind!
The bow against the wind!
Against the Wind!
Odysseus!
The bow against the wind!
Surrender yourselves to the mercy of the gods!
Pray to Poseidon!
Ask for forgiveness!
Watch out!
The last thing I remember
was Zeus's heavy hand.
Eurylochus!
I don't know what happened to them.
Yes. you know.
What he told them would happen.
I was shipwrecked on your shore. all alone.
A Shipwreck on My Shore
with the wreckage of your boat and without a crew.
Half-dead. unconscious.
I saw you looking lost.
in a few days…
And then. weeks later.
I knew the lotus would
make your awakening easier.
So that the mind hurts less than the body.
And that's exactly what happened.
You liked it so much.
You did it with such enthusiasm.
And while I was taking care of you.
Thank you.
I started to love you.
How long have I been here?
I tell myself that I shouldn't
give it to you anymore.
that you could already remember.
How much?
- He was… so happy.
You were happy.
We were so happy.
For years.
Years?
Seven years.
You gave me the lotus and held me captive.
I saved your life.
I restored your body.
But I didn't dare to restore your sanity.
He was happy.
Your heart has always been somewhere else.
And your mind would have followed suit
sooner or later.
How could you?
The lotus clouds
the mind and saps the will…
But it doesn't change you.
For some reason. you
weren't ready to come back.
And now you are.
And I always knew it would be that way.
Why?
You were clutching something
when I found you.
With a fist
clenched for weeks on end.
He was begging.
Often in Athens.
But sometimes you would say another name.
Penelope.
Help me get back.
That's what I do.
You must take control of your destiny.
But you won't be able to control that.
He was left at the mercy of the storm.
He was left at the mercy of Poseidon.
And accept your punishment.
Zeus won't let them kill you.
Give up the struggle.
give up control. and live.
This is a leap of faith that
you've never taken before. Odysseus.
Odysseus.
Where am I?
Don't you recognize your own home?
Zeus welcomes you. strangers.
How many of you are there?
Half a dozen.
Do you need something to eat?
And provisions.
For the road.
Where are you going?
We need pigs.
We're going to Pylos.
Are you pilgrims?
Do we look like pilgrims?
I can't see very well anymore.
By law. I am offering you food.
But I can't sell the pigs.
Don't worry.
We won't pay.
Please give my regards to your mother.
Say. "Please forgive me."
About Troy
and for everything that
happened in my name.
I'm sad that I haven't
heard from your father.
No. You knew.
It's not about where it is. but who it is.
And now. more than ever.
I hope to meet him.
Where are your dogs. old man?
I burn their bodies.
Can Zeus
offer you some food. traveler?
Were they attacked?
The dogs saved your servants.
No. first we burned their brothers.
What happened to Ithaca?
The Darkness.
Odysseus's law has been violated.
A kingdom without a king ever since
my master died.
Your master.
Odysseus.
A hero of the Trojan War.
But Odysseus is alive.
Beggars with false hopes!
Not anymore! Not anymore!
Not anymore! Not anymore.
Not anymore. Not anymore.
Telemachus. Telemachus…
Telemachus.
He's in danger.
And I can't help him.
There must be others in Ithaca
who can help Odysseus's son.
The grooms control the palace.
No one is
loyal to Odysseus anymore.
And what about the queen?
The beautiful.
wise Penelope.
A hostage of the worst men.
Who will force her
to get married.
What will she do
even without her son?
Here. take it. Drink up.
What danger
is Telemachus facing?
He's from Sparta.
His admirers sent thugs
to ambush him in the temple.
Give me some food for the road.
You'll never
catch up to the bandits.
If I get to Pylos before
Telemachus. I can warn him.
Why are you helping?
If I tell you. don't get mad.
I would have fought alongside Odysseus at Troy.
Really?
He was a strict master.
But fair.
It was fair. and it was worth
following it.
Did you love him?
Like his own son.
Well. he's not dead.
Is he coming home?
Soon.
To get his revenge.
Let them pay for everything.
I'll do the talking.
They don't need to know who you are.
We shouldn't have hired security.
It will help
if there are any problems.
Get moving!
I have a message.
Please wait.
Evmei sent me!
Bring the beggar here.
Your people are staying here.
And the weapons. too.
Zeus welcomes you.
Are you coming from far away?
Not quite.
Come stay the night.
We are coming to offer a sacrifice to Athena.
And the hospitality you
show will be appreciated.
Of course.
Get rid of that beggar.
He brought me a message.
Did Eumaius send you?
Yes. sir.
All right. tell me.
It's personal.
They are…
They are priests.
It's time for you to go. old man.
Go on. stranger.
I've already spared the life of
an old man this week.
But he was blind.
You won't...
It's not bad for a beggar.
No one is born a beggar.
Pick up the clothes
and put them on over the armor.
Help me with his body.
We have to leave it here.
No.
- We have to run away.
That's not how we honor him.
That's how you survive.
He was my teacher.
It may have been Athens.
as predicted.
His name was Mentor.
And now that we're safe.
We'll go to the unknown West
and we'll honor him.
The grooms sent them off.
More are on the way.
We have to go.
Overnight?
It's better than staying.
Mentor remains in the heart
of Athens' oldest temple.
For now. we'll start it with fire.
Fire!
Fire! Fire!
How is it that a beggar knows Mentor?
I already told you.
I haven't always been a beggar.
You have wise eyes.
The Eyes of Athens.
- Do not look for gods in people.
You're going to be disappointed.
Then tell me who you are.
My name is Sinon.
I am a soldier who fought
under your father's command at Troy.
Did you know my father?
I've been following his orders for as long as I can remember.
What? Is he alive?
He is alive.
And where is he?
Nearby.
He sent me to assess the situation.
My mom won't believe it.
No. you shouldn't tell her.
What do you mean. nothing?
Tell her…
Tell her that you've decided she
needs to get married now.
There's no need to test her.
How could anyone doubt her?
He has no doubt.
She would have been justified in forgetting him.
Are there any faithful servants left?
Someone.
And when Odysseus arrived—everyone.
We need to gather
the suitors at the palace.
That's never a problem.
Do you have any gifts from Menelaus?
Yes. on my ship.
Very good.
Come back as a prince.
Throw a party.
I'll be there.
What are you going to do at the party?
I'm going to beg.
You can see people better from below.
How many are there?
Tens.
But if his people are like you…
There's no one here.
What? Just you?
You. too.
Telemachus has returned.
What?
- Telemachus has returned.
Who says so?
- Everyone.
Where is Telemachus?
My queen!
But isn't your place up there?
Is that true?
He came back.
I'm back.
I was thinking we could celebrate today.
If there's anything left at all.
Don't worry.
My suitors will give us
gifts to celebrate your return.
I'm glad to see you safe and sound.
I'm glad to see you back on your feet.
It was high time
I took you to the palace.
What did you learn?
Nothing.
Stories about the war. but nothing
about what happened after they left Troy.
I'm sorry. Mom.
Everyone in Sparta is talking
about the impending disaster.
An age of darkness.
because the seafaring peoples
violate the Law of Zeus.
So it's true.
Our civilization is collapsing.
Menelaus says
that we won't be able to raise an army
with the throne vacant.
We made a plan.
What for?
So that the suitors would leave.
It's time to choose.
Do you want me to get married?
If you do that.
the others will leave.
So I'll just deal with one.
I'm almost an adult.
I will tell the elders that
I learned of Odysseus's death in Sparta.
Menelaus will support me.
and they will let me take the throne.
Your father and I left home.
To renounce.
To live with a snake.
Is that your plan? Do you have a better one?
Burn down the palace so that they will burn
the girls.
Do you think that if I get married again.
Will everything go back to normal?
This world has come to an end.
And in the new one. they won't give power
to either you or Odysseus.
If he comes back.
he'll have to kill them.
Just as you should do.
If I kill them. their
families will seek revenge.
They would have sent me into exile.
And without me. there is no throne.
Because only a man
can sit on it. right?
An empty throne?
I've been sitting there for twenty years!
My knowledge.
my many years of experience
are nothing compared to
your barely sprouting mustache.
Do you want peace?
Do you want revenge?
- I want Odysseus!
Hey…
Muzo. for one person
one person
a fleet
a war
in Troy…
Sing. Muso. about a man
a man
an idea
A little trick…
Go ahead. Eumaios.
Argos.
Bury him there. on the rock.
Where did you meet?
You are Odysseus.
You're my father.
I'm a beggar.
And you
you are the worthy one.
Odysseus's handsome son.
With whom. when they finally meet.
He'll be so proud.
Welcome home… stranger.
The Darkness of Victory
envelops the creators of legends
and turns us into blind bards and beggars.
Accept Zeus' hospitality.
Feed the stranger.
No. sir.
He'll just walk by with his bowl.
Did you really have to bring yet another
sleazy sycophant to dinner?
So what.
just another beggar at the feast?
We have to kill him before he
regains his influence among the elders.
How?
Bring some wine!
Challenge him.
Let him grab a weapon.
This isn't the pallet
we were messing with.
Then we'll go back there
tonight and slit his throat.
Get lost. old man.
- Please.
I haven't eaten in days.
Get lost!
Can't you be generous
with food that isn't yours?
There's no room in your cup.
Yes. there is.
Well. there was.
Take it.
You must be expecting something from me.
No.
I have something for you.
Do you have something for me?
There's something for me!
A filthy sycophant like you. what
Is there anything there that I might need?
Actually. it's yours.
They asked me to give it back to you.
It's not mine.
Where did you get that?
Don't turn your back on me!
Antinous. you can't
treat a beggar like that.
This is the Law of Zeus.
The Law of Zeus.
Do you think he's a god?
Is God predetermined?
Is that who you are?
Are you God.
Is that a plate or a bowl?
I am a veteran of the Trojan War.
A veteran of Troy.
And what's your name?
Synonym.
Does that name ring a bell?
I wear it in honor of the bravest
young man I ever knew.
Synonym.
Wasn't he your shepherd's son?
I don't remember.
Yeah. yeah. You wanted to go in his place.
Where did you find him?
Where you'll be soon.
And where is that?
Hades.
Enough!
The feast is over!
Let's go.
That's not mine!
The Queen would like to speak with you.
Wait until they leave
and light the fire.
Hello. traveler.
My queen.
Melanto. let Eurycleia
wash the stranger's feet.
There's no need.
My husband insisted that
we treat our guests as if they were family.
Do you know anything about Odysseus.
my husband?
From the songs.
I was in Troy. ma'am.
You probably think these songs
are silly.
They make me cry.
Why?
Because of what was lost.
Are they alive?
And the years.
Everything.
Did Odysseus meet her in Troy?
Did you notice any details about
his clothes. anything he was wearing?
She was wearing a strange brooch.
Weird?
Beautiful.
But that's beside the point.
Describe her.
I'm going to get some more water.
It was a beautiful gold brooch.
With the image of Athena.
surrounded by vines.
Did you wear it often?
You never took it off.
How come he returned home.
but Odysseus didn't?
I'm not home. Not yet. anyway.
Why not?
It's not easy to come back home.
That's true for Odysseus and for me.
Odysseus. as I knew him.
He would do even the impossible to
come back to me. no matter what.
What if Odysseus. whom
you knew. had gone missing?
What if one night.
in an unfamiliar city.
He has seen things.
that would make him think
that the home he once knew.
Could it be that it's no longer there?
When it emerges from the horse's womb
and opened the gates of Troy.
He has seen ten years of wrath.
to pour down on the city overnight?
Seven.
Everyone. now!
We left them a gift.
A gift of peace.
The ones who took you into their home.
We trampled on every sacred bond
among nations.
We turned the battle around…
Destroy their idols!
On a hunting trip.
No. please.
To burn down the walls of Troy
...was to burn the whole world to ashes.
Including his own home.
What if he had known?
that night.
walking through the flames
of anarchy and pain
and in the days that followed. filled with
exhausting celebrations…
What if he knew exactly
what he had done?
What all of you did.
One person's idea.
A man's cunning.
He broke the Law of Zeus forever.
We lived in a world of
palaces and trade.
On the word.
Blind to its beauty.
Until we destroyed it.
Are you the maritime peoples?
Yes. my queen.
Violations of the Law of
Zeus are spreading like the plague.
Our Bronze Age is coming to an end.
And perhaps he couldn't bear to
see the ruins of what had been done.
Nowhere.
And especially in my own home.
But Odysseus is alive.
And it will come
when you need it most.
Well…
I lived in its ruins for a very long time.
Bring the grooms at daybreak.
Remove the weapons from the room.
In a few hours. one of them will be happy. and
The rest will seek revenge.
The bronze is tempting.
so no weapons.
And we'll close the doors.
I will marry the one who
passes my test.
How are we going to stand up to everyone?
Just me.
Their blood is on my hands.
Or they'll send you into exile.
Don't you have one?
Don't let them get their hands on the weapons.
I'll take care of it.
Even without weapons. there are far too many of them.
Besides. you won't be armed.
I'll have a weapon.
Your mom has already taken care of it.
Gather the trusted servants.
Put the weapons away in the upstairs storage room.
Yes. I'll take care of it.
Come on. come on. Put down your weapons.
Hurry. hurry.
For Zeus. the result is what matters.
But what is the test?
For years on end.
without my husband here.
They took over the palace for their feasts.
Their proposal was to win my hand in marriage.
And as I listened to their banter and their arguments.
They were corrupting my servants
and showing no respect for my home.
All I wanted was
for Odysseus to return
and see everything with his own eyes.
But last night I realized.
that he isn't here right now.
That it will never happen.
That is why
I'm ready to marry anyone.
whoever manages to draw this bow
and shoot an arrow through
those twelve axes.
Go ahead.
And prove to me who you are.
Eumeus.
Who comes first?
Give me the bow.
It's impossible.
For you.
As a child. I saw Odysseus
do it with ease.
Go ahead and do it. then.
I'll wait my turn.
What if we heat and mash the onion?
It hasn't been stretched for years.
It's your turn.
There's no need.
The queen proved me right.
We can't replace Odysseus.
Some of us already knew that.
Some of us were going to follow
this great man to Troy.
If you had asked.
But he never did come back.
So choose the best one.
We failed your test.
I haven't failed.
Get those beggars out of here!
It is closed until the test is over.
The exam is over.
I want to give it a try.
Don't push it. old man.
No. he has the right to try.
If you don't want to. let him try.
You're making fun of
your mother's wishes.
My mom wants all of
you to burn.
He is a veteran marksman.
Hurry up.
Watch the expert in action.
Suck-up!
Hurry up!
Forget it. old man!
Hey. old man!
Hurry up!
All right. then. my friend.
That's enough. my friend.
Let him try. Let him try. Go ahead.
You're Odys…
But isn't that where you belong. down there?
Is that him?
He is.
Keep the weapons safe.
Where are the weapons?
In the warehouse upstairs.
Bring them here!
What are you waiting for?
He's going to kill us all!
Be careful!
I told you.
You're making a racket. you cowherd.
No! No! No!
Eumei! Let me out!
Down!
No!
The swords!
The shields! The shields!
Copies!
Use the copies!
Did you think you'd beat everyone?
It's enough for me to kill you.
Get it over with.
Dad!
When you arrive in Hades.
Tell my people that I'm going
west to pay my respects to them.
And tell Sinon
that I brought shame upon you.
What happened?
Did you beat them?
Is he dead?
We destroyed the fragile
bond between people.
And in the centuries of darkness to come
The stories of Troy
will be sung only…
Odysseus. my love.
Please. my love.
Odysseus.
My love. You're back.
Last but not least.
Finally.
To see my beloved
Ithaca. One last time.
No. No.
No. You can't. no.
You can't. Not right now.
Please. I've been waiting so long.
You can't die.
No. it's not death.
This is exile.
Telemachus will be king.
We'll head west. into the unknown.
to honor our people. together.
Build the fastest
ship. assemble the best
Gather your crew and set sail
toward the horizon.
We will follow
the setting sun.
A person…
Why are these stories
just going to be glorified?
Because the songs will be
the only thing they'll have.
so that they may remember those
who knew how to write.
…a war…
Civilization will be reborn.
A man…
And a new dawn will break
over the darkened world.
And our mistakes will
be forgotten once again.
Edited by bobo1974